Register of the Juraj Slávik Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
- Correspondence, 1918-1968. (Box 3-12)
  - Saint Stephen's Slovak Evangelical Lutheran Church, 1939 (Folder 10: 22)
  - The Saturday Evening Post, 1956 (Folder 10: 23)
  - Sbor Slovenského Národního Sdruženia (Slovak National Alliance), 1939 (Folder 10: 24)
  - Scaeffer Galleries, Inc., 1965 (Folder 10: 25)
  - Schwartz, John, 1965 (Folder 10: 26)
  - Sdružení Československých Dobrovolníků ve Francii (Alliance of Czechoslovak Volunteers in France), 1964 (Folder 10: 27)
  - Sdružení Československých Spolků (Alliance of Czechoslovak Unions) (Baltimore), 1953 (Folder 10: 28)
  - Sdružení Českých Spolků (Cedar Rapids), 1939 (Folder 10: 29)
  - Sdružení Čs. Učitelů a Profesorů ve Velké Británii (Association of Allied Professors and Lecturers in Great Britain), 1943 (Folder 10: 30)
  - Sdružení Uprchlíků z Podkarpatské Rusi (Union of Refugees from Subcarpathic Russia), 1955 (Folder 10: 31)
  - Seba, Jan, 1940 (Folder 10: 32)
  - Sedlák, Mirko, 1956 (Folder 10: 33)
  - Selecká, Zuzka, 1946 (Folder 10: 34)
  - Seton Hall University, 1968 (Folder 10: 35)
  - Seton-Watson, Hugh, 1943 (Folder 10: 36)
  - Sevareid, Eric, 1964 (Folder 10: 37)
  - Shaffer, Douglas, 1955 (Folder 10: 38)
  - Siegelová, Milena, 1947 (Folder 10: 39)
  - Siwek, Leonard A., 1955 (Folder 10: 40)
  - Sklizeň, 1956-1957 (Folder 10: 41)
  - Skutečnost, 1949 (Folder 10: 42)
  - Škvor, Jiří, 1955-1964 (Folder 10: 43)
  - Slabey, Andrej P., 1957-1968 (Folder 10: 44)
  - Šlechta, Vladimír, 1955 (Folder 10: 45)
  - Slezjak, Štefan, 1947 (Folder 10: 46)
  - Slovak American Charitable Association, 1965 (Folder 10: 47)
  - Slovak American Education Club, 1939 (Folder 10: 48)
  - Slovak Gymnastic Union Sokol, 1934 (Folder 10: 49)
  - Slovenská Obrana, 1939-1955 (Folder 10: 50)
  - Slovenské Národné Sdruženie (United Czechoslovakian Societies), 1939 (Folder 11: 1)
  - Slovenský Hlas, 1964 (Folder 11: 2)
  - Slovenský Samostatný v Nemoci Podporující Spolek v New Yorku (Slovak Individual Sick and Benevolent Society of New York City), 1939 (Folder 11: 3)
  - Smetánka, F., 1948 (Folder 11: 4)
  - Smutný, Jaromír, 1940 (Folder 11: 5)
  - Sonnenfeld, Peter, 1949 (Folder 11: 6)
  - Sova, Miloš, 1940-1941 (Folder 11: 7)
  - Soviet Union. Posolstvo (Great Britain), 1943 (Folder 11: 8)
  - Společnost pro Vědy a Umění (Czechoslovak Society of Arts and Sciences in America), 1945-1963 (Folder 11: 9)
  - Spolek Slovenských žen 'Živena' (Union of Slovak Women), 1945 (Folder 11: 10)
  - Sráček, Professor, 1945 (Folder 11: 11)
  - Šrámek, Jan, 1940 (Folder 11: 12)
  - Stambul, Leonid, 1956 (Folder 11: 13)
  - Stankovianský, Emil, 1942 (Folder 11: 14)
  - Státné Observatorium, 1946 (Folder 11: 15)
  - Štefánik, Paul, n.d. (Folder 11: 16)
  - Steffel, 1959 (Folder 11: 17)
  - Sterling Offices, Limited, 1945 (Folder 11: 18)
  - Sternberg, Marcel, 1948 (Folder 11: 19)
  - Straka, Palo, 1945 (Folder 11: 20)
  - Stránský, Jaroslav, 1948-1954 (Folder 11: 21)
  - Stránský, Luděk, 1949 (Folder 11: 22)
  - Středa, Francis A., 1955 (Folder 11: 23)
  - Sturc, n.d. (Folder 11: 24)
  - Sturm, Rudolf, 1953-1962 (Folder 11: 25)
  - Šulc, Jan, 1948 (Folder 11: 26)
  - Svaz Československých Racionalistů (Czechoslovak Rationalist Federation of America), 1939 (Folder 11: 27)
  - Svaz pro Chov Drobného Hospodářského Zvířectva, 1945 (Folder 11: 28)
  - Svornost, 1949 (Folder 11: 29)
  - Swanson, Hjordis, 1947 (Folder 11: 30)
  - Sýkora, O. F., 1956 (Folder 11: 31)
  - Syracuse University, 1965 (Folder 11: 32)
  - Táborský, Eduard, 1943-1965 (Folder 11: 33)
  - Taylor, Professor, 1967 (Folder 11: 34)
  - Tokoly, K., n.d. (Folder 11: 35)
  - Tono? 1952-1953 (Folder 11: 36)
  - Trinity Slovak Lutheran Church, 1954 (Folder 11: 37)
  - Trnka, Jaroslav, 1957 (Folder 11: 38)
  - Tvrdý, Bohuslav, 1945 (Folder 11: 39)
  - Uhlířová, Jarmila, 1955 (Folder 11: 40)
  - Union Internationale des Associations pour la Société des Nations, 1939 (Folder 11: 41)
  - United Empire, 1941 (Folder 11: 42)
  - United States. Congress. House of Representatives, 1951-1964 (Folder 11: 43)
  - United States. Congress. Senate, 1948-1964 (Folder 11: 44)
  - United States. Department of State, 1949 (Folder 11: 45)
  - United States. Department of the Treasury, 1947 (Folder 11: 46)
  - United States. Embassy (Czechoslovakia), 1960 (Folder 11: 47)
  - United States. Library of Congress, 1966 (Folder 11: 48)
  - United States. Office of the Vice President, 1965 (Folder 11: 49)
  - United States Information Agency, 1955-1966 (Folder 11: 50)
  - University of British Columbia, 1956 (Box-folder 12: 1)
  - University of California, Berkeley, 1948 (Folder 12: 2)
  - University of Illinois, 1965 (Folder 12: 3)
  - University of London, School of Slavonic and East European Studies, 1941 (Folder 12: 4)
  - University of Ottawa, 1961 (Folder 12: 5)
  - University of Washington, 1968 (Folder 12: 6)
  - Ústav dr. E. Beneše pro Politické a Sociální Studium (The Institute for Political and Social Studies of Dr. E. Beneš), 1956 (Folder 12: 7)
  - Ústředí Svobodných Československých Odborů(Czechoslovak Free Trade Union Center), n.d. (Folder 12: 8)
  - Ústřední Svaz Československého Studenstva v Exilu (National Union of Czechoslovak Students in Exile), 1941-1954 (Folder 12: 9)
  - Valašský, Eugen, 1959 (Folder 12: 10)
  - Valenta, Jaromír, 1950 (Folder 12: 11)
  - Vanouš, Arthur, 1955 (Folder 12: 12)
  - Varga, Bela, 1956 (Folder 12: 13)
  - Věrni Zůstaneme Sdružení Demokratických Čechoslováků (Alliance of Democratic Czechoslovaks), 1956 (Folder 12: 14)
  - Veselý, Dalimil F., 1955 (Folder 12: 15)
  - Veselý, Robert, 1959 (Folder 12: 16)
  - Viest, Ivan M., 1960 (Folder 12: 17)
  - Vitáček, Václav, 1948 (Folder 12: 18)
  - Vlach, Robert, 1956-1959 (Folder 12: 19)
  - Vnuk, František, 1960-1961 (Folder 12: 20)
  - Vrážová, Vlasta, 1961-1965 (Folder 12: 21)
  - Vymetalík, Jindřich, 1948 (Folder 12: 22)
  - Walter, Francis E., n.d. (Folder 12: 23)
  - Wandycz, Piotr, 1953 (Folder 12: 24)
  - Wechsberg, Joseph, 1956 (Folder 12: 25)
  - Wiadomosci, 1962 (Folder 12: 26)
  - Wilson, Woodrow, Mrs., 1946 (Folder 12: 27)
  - Winters, Stanley B., 1962 (Folder 12: 28)
  - WMAR-TV, Sunpapers Television, 1958 (Folder 12: 29)
  - Yugoslav Society of Great Britain, 1947 (Folder 12: 30)
  - Yugoslavia. Poslanstvo (United States), 1944 (Folder 12: 31)
  - Zedtwitz, Dr., n.d. (Folder 12: 32)
  - Zeman, Jan, 1960 (Folder 12: 33)
  - Zenkl, Petr, 1964 (Folder 12: 34)
  - Zich, Jaroslav V., 1954 (Folder 12: 35)
  - Zima, Stephen, 1957 (Folder 12: 36)
  - Zivena, 1945 (Folder 12: 37)
  - Znojemský, n.d. (Folder 12: 38)
  - Zoutchan, Jožko, 1940 (Folder 12: 39)
- Speeches and Writings, 1933-1966. (Box 13-38)
  Articles, notes, papers, radio broadcast transcripts, reports, speeches, and writings, arranged chronologically by title
  - General
    - Unidentified writings
      - Fragments (Folder 13: 1-6)
      - Loose leaves (Box-folder 14: 1-7)
      - Loose leaves (Box-folder 15: 1-3)
    - Christmas writings (Folder 15: 4)
    - Letters to the editor, n.d.
      Holographs and typescripts (in English and Slovak)
      - Čechoslovák (Folder 15: 5)
      - Naše Hlasy (Folder 15: 6)
      - The New York Herald Tribune (Folder 15: 7)
      - The New York Times (Folder 15: 8)
      - The Saturday Evening Post (Folder 15: 9)
      - Skutečnost (Folder 15: 10)
      - Věstník Československé Národní Rady Americké (Folder 15: 11)
      - The Washington Post and Times Herald (Folder 15: 12)
      - Miscellaneous (Folder 15: 13)
    - Notes (Box-folder 16: 1-5)
    - Notes (Box-folder 17: 1-2)
    - Poetry (Folder 17: 3-4)
    - Transcripts of radio broadcasts., See also memoirs "Moja pamať - živá kniha," 1955-1957 (Box 18)
      - British Broadcasting Corporation (BBC)
        - Czechoslovak Programme
          - Undated (Folder 18: 1-2)
          - 1941 (Folder 18: 3)
          - 1942 (Folder 18: 4)
          - 1943 (Folder 18: 5)
          - 1944 (Folder 18: 6)
          - 1945 (Folder 18: 7)
        - Hungarian Programme (Folder 18: 8)
        - Miscellaneous. (Folder 18: 9)
          Includes instructions to commentators
      - National Broadcasting Corporation (NBC), The World Front (Box-folder 19: 1)
      - Radio Free Europe, Czechoslovak Desk
        - 1952-1956 (Folder 19: 2)
        - 1957-1963 (Folder 19: 3)
      - Miscellaneous (Folder 19: 4)
    - Miscellaneous speeches, n.d. (Folder 19: 5-7)
    - Miscellaneous speeches, n.d. (Box-folder 20: 1-5)
  - "11. november 1939 a druhý odboj," n.d. (Box-folder 21: 1)
    Typescript (in Slovak)
  - "Ady, revolucionár," n.d. (Folder 21: 2)
    Holograph and typescript (in Slovak)
  - "Aesop's Fables in Czechoslovakia," n.d. (Folder 21: 3)
    Holograph and typescript
  - "Ako a kde sa osadiali Slováci v Spojených Státech Severní Ameriky?" n.d. (Folder 21: 4)
    Holograph (in Slovak)
  - "Ako je to so Sidorom?" n.d. (Folder 21: 5)
  - "Alphonse Mucha, the First Designer of Czechoslovak Stamps and a Grand-Master of Masons in Czechoslovakia," n.d. (Folder 21: 6)
    Typescript
  - "Americká armáda v Československu v roku 1945," n.d. (Folder 21: 7)
  - "Autorita Dr. Eduarda Beneša," n.d. (Folder 21: 8)
  - "Biskup Vladimír P. Cobrda 70-ročný," n.d. (Folder 21: 9)
  - "Češi a Slováci," n.d. (Folder 21: 10)
    Typescript (in English and Slovak)
  - "Československá zahraniční vláda presidenta Dra E. Beneša v Londýně a Slovenské národné povstanie," n.d. (Folder 21: 11)
  - "Church Freedom in Europe," n.d. (Folder 21: 12)
  - "Conversations in Moscow in the Years 1943, 1944, 1945," n.d. (Folder 21: 13)
  - "Ctený pan Stankowianský," n.d. (Folder 21: 14)
    Holograph
  - "Cultural Institutions and Cultural Achievements of Czechoslovak Emigres in the Free World," n.d. (Folder 21: 15)
  - "Cultural Resistance," n.d. (Folder 21: 16)
  - "Czechoslovak President Dr. Eduard Beneš Makes an Attempt to Reach a Polish-Czechoslovak Settlement in September 1938," n.d. (Folder 21: 17)
  - "The Death of a Hero," n.d. (Folder 21: 18)
  - "Devedesiaté výročie narodenia Dra. Pavla Bláhu," n.d. (Folder 21: 19)
  - "The Development in Great Britain till May 1943: A New Hungarian Club in London," n.d. (Folder 21: 20)
  - "Dobrá věc se podařila," n.d. (Folder 21: 21)
    Holograph (in Czech)
  - "Dohodnúť sa!" n.d. (Folder 21: 22)
  - "Drahí slovenskí rodáci," n.d. (Folder 21: 23)
  - "Dva jazyky Zdeňka Nejedlého," n.d. (Folder 21: 24)
    Typescript and clipping (in Slovak)
  - "Dve slovenské evanjelické jubileja: Karol Kuzmany a Juraj Janoska," n.d. (Folder 21: 25)
  - "East-South Contacts," n.d. (Folder 21: 26)
  - "Eduard Beneš: The Great Tragic Figure of Czechoslovakia," n.d. (Folder 21: 27)
  - "A Few Remarks to the Hearings Before the Subcommittee to Investigate the Administration of the Internal Security Act and Other Internal Security Laws of the Committee on the Judiciary, United States Senate, Eighty-Second Congress, First and Second Sessions on Espionage Activities of the Personnel Attached to Embassies and Consulates Under Soviet Dominations in the United States," n.d. (Box-folder 22: 1)
  - "Freedom of Speech," n.d. (Folder 22: 2)
  - "Hungarians from Czechoslovakia," n.d. (Folder 22: 3)
  - "Inside Czechoslovakia," n.d. (Folder 22: 4)
  - "Jak vypadaly májové oslavy v Praze ve skutečnosti," n.d. (Folder 22: 5)
    Typescript (in Czech)
  - "Janko Jesenský v druhom zahraničnom odboji," n.d. (Folder 22: 6)
  - "Jaroslav Šejnoha 75-ročný," n.d. (Folder 22: 7)
  - "Jean-Jacques Rousseau and His Social Contract," n.d. (Folder 22: 8)
  - "Jednota," n.d. (Folder 22: 9)
  - "Kdo porazil nacizmus?" n.d. (Folder 22: 10)
  - "Kulturný prínos ČSR na Slovensku," n.d. (Folder 22: 11)
  - "Locke and His Philosophy," n.d. (Folder 22: 12)
  - "Madari v Spojených Štátoch Severnej Ameriky," n.d. (Folder 22: 13)
  - "Maďarská statistika," n.d. (Folder 22: 14)
  - "Manifest Slovákov v zahraničnom boji," n.d. (Folder 22: 15)
  - "Masarykovo státnické umenie," n.d. (Folder 22: 16)
  - "Mnichov a co po ňom následovalo," n.d. (Folder 22: 17)
  - "My, Čechoslováci v emigracii," n.d. (Folder 22: 18)
  - "Nevyřešený problém," n.d. (Folder 22: 19)
  - "Niekolko poznámok k I. A II. Svazku Vybraných spisov Františka Votrubu: Akýsi doslov k prvému svazku mojích pametí," n.d. (Folder 22: 20)
  - Note on Adam Pribicevic, n.d. (Folder 22: 21)
  - Note on Hubert Ripka, Československá akce v zahraničí, n.d. (Folder 22: 22)
    Holograph and typescript (in Czech)
  - Notes on Štefan Osuský, Beneš a Slovensko, n.d. (Folder 22: 23)
  - "Nový román Mila Urbana," book review, n.d. (Folder 22: 24)
  - "Od rezistencie k povstaniu," n.d. (Folder 22: 25)
  - "Odpoveď Jozefu Huskovi," n.d. (Folder 22: 26)
  - "Odpoveď na posolstvo Dra Jozefa Tisu," n.d. (Folder 22: 27)
  - "Ohlas k americkým Slovákom," n.d. (Folder 22: 28)
  - "Osemdesiate výročie narodenia prezidenta Eduarda Beneša," n.d. (Folder 22: 29)
  - "Oskar Kokoschka: Čech," n.d. (Folder 22: 30)
  - "Pamiatke bratra - Sokola, Bohumila Tesara," n.d. (Folder 22: 31)
  - "Pat rokov od smrti generála Antonína B. Hasala," n.d. (Folder 22: 32)
  - "Pavol Orszagh Hviezdoslav," n.d. (Folder 22: 33)
    Holograph and typescript(in Slovak)
  - "The People-To-People Program," n.d. (Folder 22: 34)
  - "Perzekucia a sabotáž v ČSR," n.d. (Folder 22: 35)
  - "Poláci jsou odhodláni se bránit," n.d. (Folder 22: 36)
  - "Polské vzpomienky," n.d. (Folder 22: 37)
  - "Poznámky k 70 narodeninám Kazimierza Baginského," n.d. (Folder 22: 38)
  - "Pre věrnych Čechoslovákov," n.d. (Folder 22: 39)
  - "Predvianočne rozjímanie," n.d. (Folder 22: 40)
  - "Přítel z jiného břehu: Poznámka k článku Otakara Odložilíka," n.d. (Box-folder 23: 1)
  - "Pronásledování církví," n.d. (Folder 23: 2)
  - "Protectorate Slovakia," n.d. (Folder 23: 3)
  - "Protektorát," n.d. (Folder 23: 4)
  - Radio speech to Poland, n.d. (Folder 23: 5)
    Holograph and typescript (in English, Czech, and Polish)
  - Remarks on Julien Benda, Zrada vzdělanců, n.d. (Folder 23: 6)
  - Review of Carlile Aylmer Macartney, Problems of the Danube Basin, n.d. (Folder 23: 7)
  - Review of Donald Alexander Lowrie, The Hunted Children, n.d. (Folder 23: 8)
  - Review of Jan Křen, Do emigrace: Buržoazní zahraniční odboj, n.d. (Folder 23: 9)
  - Review of Judith Listowel, Z maďarskej propagandy v Anglii, n.d. (Folder 23: 10)
  - Review of R. Kopecký, Československý odboj v Polsku v roce 1939, n.d. (Folder 23: 11)
  - Review of William L. Shirer, The Rise and Fall of the Third Reich, n.d. (Folder 23: 12)
    Holograph and typescript (in English and Slovak)
  - "Rozhlasový projev k státním a verejným zamestnancom," radio speech, n.d. (Folder 23: 13)
  - "Sano Mach," radio speech broadcast, Czechoslovak B.B.C. Radio, n.d. (Folder 23: 14)
  - "Slovakia within the Czechoslovak Republic," n.d. (Folder 23: 15)
  - "Slovenské národné povstanie," n.d. (Folder 23: 16)
  - "Slovenské Vianoce," n.d. (Folder 23: 17)
  - "Slovensko až do dneška," n.d. (Folder 23: 18-20)
  - "Slovenský spisovatel Daniel Z. Laucek v Americe," n.d. (Box-folder 24: 1)
  - "Slovo na cestu," n.d. (Folder 24: 2)
  - "Sokolstvo a Slováci," n.d. (Folder 24: 3)
  - Speech, 25th anniversary of the Czech-American Center, Washington, D.C., n.d. (Folder 24: 4)
  - Speech, 25th anniversary of the founding of the Cyril and Method Church, Newark, New Jersey, n.d. (Folder 24: 5)
  - Speech, art exhibition, Czechoslovak Research Institute, London, n.d. (Folder 24: 6)
  - Speech, Columbia University, n.d. (Folder 24: 7)
  - Speech, International Pen Club, London, n.d. (Folder 24: 8)
  - Speech, poetry meeting, n.d. (Folder 24: 9)
  - Speech in memory of Anton P. Ambre, n.d. (Folder 24: 10)
  - Speech in memory of General Sergej Ingr, n.d. (Folder 24: 11)
  - Speech on the coup d'état, Chicago, n.d. (Folder 24: 12)
  - Speech on the Slovak uprising, n.d. (Folder 24: 13)
  - Speech to Rotarian friends from Allied countries, Czechoslovak Institute, London, n.d. (Folder 24: 14)
  - "Štefan Krčmery zomrel," n.d. (Folder 24: 15)
  - "Sto rokov od narodenia Martina Kukučína," New Yorkský Denník, n.d. (Folder 24: 16)
    Printed copy
  - "Sub-Carpatho-Russia," n.d. (Folder 24: 17)
  - "T. G. Masaryk a dnešek," n.d. (Folder 24: 18)
  - "Tretia armáda generála Pattona v Československu," n.d. (Folder 24: 19)
  - "Úkoly mladé inteligencie dnes a v oslobodenej vlasti," n.d. (Folder 24: 20)
  - "Úplné fiasko katolickej akcie na Slovensku," n.d. (Folder 24: 21)
  - "V historickej chvili: K polsko-československým stykom," n.d. (Folder 24: 22)
  - "V nový život," n.d. (Folder 24: 23)
  - "Věčná mladosť: K sedemdesiatým narodzeninám sestry Marie Provazníkové," n.d. (Folder 24: 24)
  - "Vytrváme a zvítazíme," n.d. (Folder 24: 25)
  - "Z Podkarpatskej Rusi: Z listů z domova," n.d. (Folder 24: 26)
  - "Zdeněk Němeček," speech, n.d. (Folder 24: 27)
  - "Zdvíhal svoj varovný prst v napomínání," n.d. (Folder 24: 28)
  - "Židia na nacistickom Slovensku, n.d. (Folder 24: 29)
  - Speech on the bill relating to the cessation of activities and dissolution of political parties, Czechoslovak Parliament, 1933 October 20. (Folder 24: 30)
  - "Ohlas k americkým Slovákom," New Yorkský Denník, 1939 April 21. (Folder 24: 31)
  - Speech commemorating Czechoslovak soldiers who died during the first year of the Second World War, 1940. (Folder 24: 32)
  - "Vzácné jubileum," 1940. (Folder 24: 33)
  - "K sjazdu československých učitelov," 1941. (Folder 24: 34)
  - Peace Treaties and Central Europe, lecture, New Europe Forum, London, 1941 April 28. (Folder 24: 35)
    Typescript and printed copy
  - Speech commemorating Jan Hus, Anglo-Czechoslovak Christian Fellowship meeting, Westminster, 1941 July 6. (Folder 24: 36)
  - Speech commemorating the 2nd anniversary of the International Students Day, 1941 November 17. (Folder 24: 37)
  - Speech, Royal Empire Society, London, 1941 November 18. (Box-folder 25: 1)
  - Speech, Oxford, 1941 November 20. (Folder 25: 2)
  - Speech on the persecution of churches in Czechoslovakia, 1942? (Folder 25: 3)
  - Speech, Masaryk Society, Cambridge, 1942 January. (Folder 25: 4)
  - Speech, Czechoslovak Army and Air Force Concert, Newport and Cardiff, South Wales, 1942 February 14. (Folder 25: 5)
    Includes correspondence with Lord Plymouth and the Czechoslovak Centre for South Wales. Typescript
  - Speech commemorating the 350th anniversary of the birth of John Amos Comenius, Birmingham, 1942 March 28. (Folder 25: 6)
    Typescript. Includes Slávik's speech on the German invasion of Czechoslovakia and correspondence with the Lord Mayor of Birmingham
  - Speech on the occasion of the formation of the Czecho-slovak-British Society, Glasgow, 1942 April 28. (Folder 25: 7)
    Holograph, typescript and clippings (in English and Slovak), and correspondence with itinerary. Included are also speeches in St. Andrews and Edinburgh, as part of a lecture tour on education in Czechoslovakia
  - Speech commemorating Lidice, Lidice Memorial Settlement, Dorchester, 1942 October 12. (Folder 25: 8)
  - Speech in commemoration of the Czechoslovak Independence Day, Concert of Slavonic Music organized by Friends of Czechoslovakia and Czechoslovak Centre, Manchester, 1942 October 24. (Folder 25: 9)
    Typescript. Includes correspondence with the Czechoslovak Centre in Manchester
  - "Europe: Prison of the Apocalypse," speech, the Women's Section of the British Legion annual meeting, The Norfolk Chronicle, 1942 November 4. (Folder 25: 10)
    Correspondence with Gweneth and Thomas Cook, and printed copy
  - Speech honoring Bjornstern Bjornston, Czechoslovak Research Institute, 1942 December 8. (Folder 25: 11)
  - Radio speech on Slovaks fighting in Russia, 1943. (Folder 25: 12)
  - "Štvrtročie republiky," radio speech, 1943. (Folder 25: 13)
  - Československo: Zemský ráj - nacistické peklo, Lofox, Ltd., London, 1943 January. (Folder 25: 14)
  - Speech upon the 4th anniversary of 15 March 1939, 1943 March 15? (Folder 25: 15)
  - "Eisteddfod y Cymry," 1943 August. (Folder 25: 16)
  - Speech commemorating the 25th anniversary of the founding of the Czechoslovak Republic, 1943 October. (Folder 25: 17)
  - "Prejav do polského radia," 1943 October 28 (Folder 25: 18)
  - "Kulturný prínos ČSR na Slovensku," Slovenský sokol, 1943 December 23. (Folder 25: 19)
    Printed copy (in Slovak)
  - "United Nations Educational Organisation," The Spirit of Czechoslovakia, London, 1944. (Folder 25: 20)
    Holograph, typescript, and printed copy (in English and Slovak)
  - "Slovenský odpor v r. 1943," 1944 January. (Folder 25: 21)
  - Speech, the Royal Empire Society, 1944 January 12. (Folder 25: 22)
    Holograph and typescript (in English and Slovak). Includes correspondence with the Royal Empire Society
  - Speech, Association of Czechoslovak Advocates Abroad, 1944 January 31. (Folder 25: 23)
  - Speech, manifestation organized by the State Council, London, 1944 February 8. (Folder 25: 24)
  - Speech at the reception for the officers of the British Royal Navy, Czechoslovak Institute, London, 1944 May 5. (Folder 25: 25)
  - Letter to the editor, Nové Československo, 1944 August 21. (Folder 25: 26)
  - Speech, Danish-Czechoslovak Committee, Czechoslovak Institute, London, 1944 October 23. (Folder 25: 27)
  - Speech, Reception, Czechoslovak Economic Association, 1945 March 1. (Box-folder 26: 1)
  - Speech on the opening of the Art Exhibition of Karel Fogl and Bedrich Feigl, London, 1945 March 9. (Folder 26: 2)
  - Speech, 1945 April 13. (Folder 26: 3)
  - "Jan Ámos Komenský v Anglii," 1945 July 16. (Folder 26: 4)
  - "Prezident Dr. Beneš v zahraničí," New Yorkský Denník, 1946 May 28. (Folder 26: 5)
    Typescript and printed copy (in Slovak)
  - "Naše stanovisko v židovské otázce je jasné," Lidová demokracie, 1946 October 2. (Folder 26: 6)
  - Speech, American Friends of Czechoslovakia, New York, 1946 October 28. (Folder 26: 7)
  - Speech on "CARE" organization, 1947 March 3. (Folder 26: 8)
  - Speech on the struggle of churches and religious organizations against nazism, The Covenant-First Presbytarian Church, Washington, D.C., 1947 March 20. (Folder 26: 9)
  - "Czechoslovakia's Man of Liberty," The Christian Register Unitarian, 1947 May. (Folder 26: 10)
  - Speech, United Jewish Appeal dinner, New York, 1947 June 11. (Folder 26: 11)
  - Speech on peaceful coexistence with the Soviets, 1948? (Folder 26: 12)
  - Speech on the occasion of the 30th anniversary of the founding of the Czechoslovak Republic, Newark, New Jersey, 1948 (Folder 26: 13)
  - Speech, Grace Lutheran Church, Washington, D.C., 1948 March 8. (Folder 26: 14)
  - "Jan Garrigue Masaryk," speech remembering Jan Masaryk at the Memorial Service, All Souls' Church, Washington, D.C., 1948 March 14. (Folder 26: 15)
    Holograph and typescript. Includes other writings on Jan Masaryk on various occasions
  - "Munich: Peace with Honor?" 1948 August 21. (Folder 26: 16)
  - "Eduard Beneš," letter to the editor, The Washington Post, 1948 September 10. (Folder 26: 17)
  - "Národ a strany," Svobodný zítřek, 1948 November 2. (Folder 26: 18)
    Holograph, typescript, and printed copy
  - "Col. Carl Lukas, Former Czechoslovak Military Attache, Died in Prison," 1949. (Folder 26: 19)
  - Letter to the editor, The Washington Post, 1949 June 16. (Folder 26: 20)
  - Letter to the editor, Skutečnost, 1949 July 29. (Folder 26: 21)
  - Speech, International Crossroads Sunday Morning Breakfast, Y.M.C.A., 1950 March 26. (Folder 26: 22)
  - Speech, 50th anniversary of Slovak literary circle 'Národ,' New York, 1950 December 3. (Folder 26: 23)
  - Letter to the editor, The New York Times, 1950 August 10. (Folder 26: 24)
  - "Kulturná bilancia komunizmu v Československu," draft of a radio speech commemorating the February 1948 putch, 1951 February. (Folder 26: 25)
  - Letter to the editor, The New York Herald Tribune, 1952 (Folder 26: 26)